software engineering radio episode 39
interview with Stefano ski
[Music]
hi everybody
this is a new episode of software
engineering radio another interview
episode today we are pleased to welcome
Stefano ski on the podcast steve is the
chief engineer of product innovation for
Iona technologies diode on technologies
you might know it's a quite well known
middleware vendor and Steve is actually
at what you'd call a middleware guru
he's been involved with Korb acquired a
bit he is now working with so on
enterprise integration and messaging so
in this episode we are mainly going to
talk about various aspects of middleware
and core Bob so we wanna thank Steve for
agreeing to be on the podcast and yeah
have fun listening by the way I just
wanted to mention we have recorded this
episode also at the Chou conference in
October 2006 and our host and Mark so
again you might hear some background
noise from the exhibition area the
quality is still really good I think so
yeah have fun listening ok Steve welcome
to this interview on soft engineering
radio thank you
as our listeners might have guessed
already we're probably going to talk
mostly about middleware since you're
definitely a middleware person so how
did you get first involved in building
middleware communication infrastructure
what's your background there ok I was at
Apollo computer in the late 1980s and I
was actually working on hardware so I
have an electrical engineering
background I started out making helping
make chips at TI you know and I fell in
love with software so over time I moved
more and more into software so at Apollo
I was working on a system that was a
diagnostic system that would let a
remote user debug the hardware it was
called rise it was remote interactive
scan environment scan technology is a
certain hardware technology for testing
and so rise or rice plus plus actually
was written in C++ but it had a tickle
front end where he had commands that you
could issue the thing so you could sit
at a workstation
Apollo workstation that would be you
know fully up and running and everything
the machine you're working on is
completely shut down and just had a
small like 20k RPC server inside in a it
was a diagnostic CPU and that was like
my first distributed system I had to
write the protocol to do that and
shortly after that HP bought Apollo and
they kind of you know shifted things
around got rid of the group I was in so
I had to find something else to do and
that's when Corbeau was starting up and
that group was Jim Waldo was the
technical leader that was at HP MoMA you
have the core of a development at HP
okay okay and it was the only group I
knew of in the company or where I was in
Massachusetts that was actually writing
C++ code so I joined there and the rest
is history so how many orbs did you
actually implement so let's see I think
the count is six
when I was at HP the group there built
the first kind of prototype or for the
OMG before the core respec was finished
just great I want to show yeah okay kind
of show what it was or what it would be
like and I joined the group right as
they finished that one so I don't count
that one but then we worked on a couple
more in that group and then over time
you know the group changed and got
different managers and different you
know pushed into different organizations
and stuff and they never really sold any
of the orbs until probably the mid-90s
and by then we had written three or four
five and then I went to Iona and I have
to worked on the one their orbits mm or
Orbach six is called now so I think it's
six so how did they differ over time
obviously you learn from doing the
previous ones but what's kind of the
major differences I think
the the early ones were built on
previous technology so Apollo had a
networked computing system that evolved
NCS went into DCE
NCS network computing system IBC is a
distributed communications environment
right so DCE was bigger than just NCS
but NCS played a major role other parts
from dec came into DCE as well so the
early orbs were all built on top of DCE
basically yeah it's sort of like taking
that fundamental infrastructure and then
putting a different API on top of it and
DCE and NCS both had this sort of
little-known feature that they could
actually do distributed objects they
weren't usually used that way they were
used as pure RPC systems but they had in
the protocol of a field for an object
identifier basically so you could target
specific objects so the early ones made
use of that as we went on you know the
core respect matured and I remember
sitting around you know kind of sitting
there thinking what are these type code
things you know what are they what are
they meant to be because the spec wasn't
very clear it came from that part of the
spec came from other vendors not from HP
and son HP and son were doing joint
development back then it was all the
static side of CORBA you know came from
us and then this dynamic invocations
taking from a hyper desk and and Digital
Equipment Corporation so we were kind of
puzzling you know we know how to build
the static side but how do you build
this type code and di also struggled
with that for a long time it's funny
looking back on it now it's so simple
you know once we figured out what they
were but over time the infrastructure
shifted away from using VCE
to
IOP building your own kind of your own
listeners and your own handlers of
requests and dispatchers and everything
else it was just a learning process over
time of figuring out what the spec was
trying to do tightening up the spec so
while we're implementing these things
we're also in the OMG kind of you know
can we fix this can we fix that so you
mentioned before that that DCE basically
was like distributed api stateless and
Carvell provided these object notions
now current hype tomorrow's more or less
goes back to services so uh and also
probably carve our best practices will
tell you that you should use rather
coarse-grained kind of more component
like maybe stateless objects instead of
having these fine grained objects so how
successful was the the object in the
part of CORBA actually was did the right
direction no that's a right notion to
communicate right that's that's a hard
question I think it really depends on
what you were trying to do with it you
know there were certain systems that
were very successful with that
particular approach and you know having
stateful objects versus stateless
objects and the granularity and stuff as
people struggled with all that for four
years if you look at systems like you
know the services like the naming
service or you know the standard kind of
Corvus services
those are object oriented distributed
object and you know people work with
them and they work really well it
certainly have plenty of customers that
you know lots of telcos and
manufacturing and finance companies that
have used korva and they they kind of
get it after a while and they they find
a way that works for them reason I was
asking was that these you know if you
have objects and you distribute the
responsibilities you know as CRC cars
basically tell you then you get a lot of
fine grained interactions and these
obviously don't scale over the network
so there's the
friends kind of yeah I think there's a
bit of a backlash right now for
distributed objects and you know
services are sort of ignoring all that
stuff again they're just saying you know
here's the service over here and go call
it and you know people want stateless
services naturally because they're
easier to scale yeah and so I think the
distributed object paradigm has gotten
kind of a bad name but that's natural
when when technology shifts you kind of
have to have to play down the previous
one yeah so I don't think that it's
necessarily wrong or bad it's you know
for certain applications it's exactly
right and you know pretty much for
example at any time you make a phone
call in most parts of the world you're
going through some core of a software in
some fashion yeah and you know the
stuffs gonna be around for another 15 or
20 years anyway in those in those
systems which brings us to the question
of the future of Karva but first I'd
like to go back briefly about the
implementation in orbs we all know this
disposer to book right those patterns
for distributed systems right how many
of these patterns have you actually used
or which you know which are the most
important or critical ones can you kind
of characterize that well I don't know
if I can recall the the pattern names
off the top of my head but I believe I
was a reviewer for that book before it
was published and I just remembered as I
went through the book kind of going wow
you know this is exactly right yes we
use this we use this use this and it
very well you know succinctly captured a
lot of the work that we had done through
basically through the 90s on building
these systems and yeah so I think you
know a lot of Doug Schmidt's work for
example in the papers he put together
and just you know people attacking this
issue trying to figure out what the
patterns were and characterize them and
write them down and again it's like that
type code thing that I mentioned when
you read the patterns now you just go
well of course you do it that way but to
get there
it took quite a while so that book in
particular is very it's a very accurate
kind of collection of the patterns that
you do use yeah I think sometimes you
run into people look at patterns books
and say well do we really use these
things and in that case yes yeah pretty
much all of them it so okay now what is
the future of Carbaugh my personal
impression is that it's more or less
happening in technical and embedded
systems these days and write much in
business areas I think what's happening
is in terms of the you can look at
different ways in the OMG
a lot of the corba development is in the
real-time embedded space yeah so those
are the guys and and that makes sense
you know because the market for CORBA in
the enterprise is mature but the market
for Corbin in real time those guys are
more conservative yeah so they're kind
of now getting to trust it and so for
them it's kind of a newer thing yeah so
in the OMG a lot of what's happening in
Corbett does get directed by by that
that domain yeah in the market we still
see you know some people picking it up
and again it's the more conservative
customer yeah you know in asia-pacific
for example it's very popular for them
korba is relatively new in a way so I
keep getting asked to go to Beijing we
have an office in Beijing and they keep
saying Steve you need to come over to
Beijing because there's all these CORBA
fans who want to meet you and it's just
a long trip I don't know if I'd want to
do it but so different parts of the
world have also kind of a different view
on where the Corbeau market is yeah yeah
so can you maybe briefly explain what
the difference is between the normal
core ba and real-time core by maybe
minimum carb RR well I'm not sure of all
the details but I mean normal core go
has you know all the features that its
accrued over the years
minimal korva is sort of like you know
what do we really need to get a system
up in
or you know one of the features we use
most and you can drop a lot of features
that you know kind of make the whole
thing more complex I Pro combi dynamic
stuff yeah right in the in the embedded
world in fact most
corba applications use the static
approach and the dynamic approach is
good if you need it but if you don't
need it it's kind of like you can just
throw it throw it aside a lot of the
code that you have to write to implement
the dynamic stuff it's well once you
figure it out again like type code it's
not that hard it's just very tedious and
it's very large yeah a lot of yeah and
if you can take that out you're
obviously going to save your application
space and quicker load times all that
stuff so and then the real time Corbeau
well you know real-time embedded systems
they have to deal with priorities and
making sure the you don't have priority
inversion issues and things like that so
request priorities and deadlines through
the the system yeah priority propogation
right so it's really more about making
sure that there's nothing in the
specification that would kind of prevent
the the right thing from happening in
that regard so it's the OMG working on
some kind of modernized Corvo for
example the language mappings especially
for C++ and Java have been criticized a
lot for it for the verbosity and stuff
is there something happening or is it
pretty much you know that's how it is my
opinion is they they won't change them I
think the issue is first of all it this
issue comes up in the OMG every couple
years
someone says we've got to fix these
mappings yeah and no one is objecting
you know but people say well are the
vendors really going to pick up the new
map bones and implement them yeah the
OMG has a policy now that if you issue
if they adopt a technology as a standard
they have to have I think at least one
implementation of it before it'll be
adopted like it won't even be adopted at
all if there's no nobody implement
thing my standards and so I think people
are worried the vendors would not
implement it now the open-source IRB's
may implement because they have more
flexibility like with with our orbit
this orb for example which is not open
source but source available yeah we
could maybe do something like that but
our customers really don't want to have
to go retool their code because again
it's kind of it's already out there it's
deployed they're not really actively
developing it but they're actively using
it so if it's gonna happen it would
happen in the real time area because
again that's where the action is in
terms of court my involvement in the OMG
I haven't been to a meeting in a while
now the last thing I worked on was
Corbeau reflection which became a
standard is actually something that that
I did kind of single-handedly almost
well that's not entirely true there was
a Frank pill offer of mercury systems
helped me out quite a bit with the
reflection but it was something that I
put into the OMG is an RFC and the
reason I put it in or what it is it's
really introspection yeah so an object
should have all of its metadata
available at runtime and it actually
does have its metadata available at
runtime but it's never been exposed
before and because we were trying to
take our customers forward into the
world of web services so we want to keep
all their korva objects and systems
running but be able to get at them
through web services applications I
needed a way to go to an object
corporate object and just say give me or
metadata give me your IDL basically yeah
and you could do that through the
interface repository standard part of
korva but nobody really implements it
and it's another process that would have
to be running somewhere and most
operators don't want to do that at you
know in production yeah so this way the
data the metadata is already in the
object because it's used for dispatching
and marshalling and stuff so this is
just an interface
utilizing the data yeah that you could
ask an object say are you first are you
reflective can can I you narrow to a
reflection interface and if that works
then you can ask it for the for its
metadata and you can get it in the form
of an interface repository struct that
has everything in it so all the data
about based interfaces all the
operations all the parameters you know
everything like that or you could
actually get it back as XML and I know a
lot of people go ooh the XML that's bad
but when you're dealing with Web
Services you're already dealing with XML
so you can actually pull the XML and
it's a representation of the metadata
that's in the object so you already
mentioned Web Services you know the the
question are they gonna replace carbon
but what's your opinion there won't be
as fast as efficient you know I think
there are some reasonably fast soap
stacks we have an open source project
currently in the Apache Incubator that a
lot of Iona engineers are contributing
to called Celtics fire and Celtics fires
combination of two projects one was
Celtics that we did in the object web
open source community and then Xfire
which was a believe a code house and
Xfire is called the fastest soap stack
on the planet all right so we combine
the two and it's again in the Apache
Incubator and I just saw some figures on
the performance and so if you compare
the performance of Celtics fire to
Celtics you know there's quite a huge
difference improvement and I don't know
that it will ever be as fast as Corbeau
systems you know there are especially
some of the embedded or real-time
systems that are departing is really
really really fast and but the point
about Web Services I don't think they're
really meant as a replacement for korba
I think Web Services is more about kind
of a higher level of integration than
Corbett did
with our we have the Arctic's product
for example at Iona and what it does is
it uses web services as an abstraction
of kind of middleware so middleware of
middleware yeah you might have a CORBA
object that you need to get talking to
some tuxedo service yeah you know and
maybe there's some MQ and your
enterprise and TIBCO and things like
that so this what Arctic's can do is
sort of abstract all that and make the
development of service-oriented systems
such that your programming against the
wisdom and all the details of the
transports and the the protocols
underneath are all hidden so you know
you might have one call going over I up
and then the next call to this other
service going over MQ you know and and I
think you know for I suppose you could
technically say that CORBA could do that
because I OP was just one protocol that
korva could have supported but it's also
the model of programming you know
there's the IDL versus the wisdom and
coupling issues and yeah and again back
into language mappings and stuff like
that so there are differences and and
people seem to like Arctic's it's a
little hard to explain because it's
classified as an Enterprise Service bus
where most Enterprise Service buses are
these centralized kind of hub oriented
systems glorified JMS you know our
system is extensible and distributed and
there's really no central bus or Club so
it's a little hard to explain yeah
maybe also due to the fact that nobody
really knows what an enterprise service
bus well yeah that's that's also an
issue I suppose so
do you consider web service is more like
RPC with angle brackets or do you think
it's more like messaging or how do you
what would you classify I think over
time it's changed so when I first
started you know I've known Don box for
many years and he kind of called me on
the phone and said we're putting the
soap thing together and would you like
to look at it so we took a look at it
and
it's kind of interesting and you know I
think the thing about it was it was just
an another way of getting messages from
one point to another and sort of you
know he had these wars between Corbin
and calm and you know they didn't sort
of get get along and stuff like that so
so initially started out as our PC and
very much oriented around the same kinds
of things that Corbin comm were already
doing but I think over time people
realize that if you're dealing with XML
you you're really dealing with documents
right and so it's evolved I would say to
a document passing system yeah now
that's not to say that people aren't
doing RPC with it that's actually one of
my pet peeves is this impedance mismatch
of trying to map XML into objects or
vice versa yeah and it's just come from
years of struggling with that mapping
issue I've written a number of columns
about it and in my blog and you know
whenever when every chance I get there
you go so I think the more advanced web
service developers are passing messages
around documents specifically and they
deal with documents they don't try to
convert it into Java or into C++ or
whatever it is they they use it as a
document and in that case it's not so
much RPC anymore that's really more like
messaging so that's also where I think
one of the really you know measurable
advantages of web services or document
oriented communication lies that if you
for example take a car by arielle
structure interface all the structures
are compiled into the stops so if you
evolve the definition of the struct
basically your your op crashes or
something like that if you have an
interpreted data structure you're much
more flexible you don't have to rebuild
the infrastructure to evolve the
document structure right that gets into
versioning which is a really hard
problem as you know private wide stop
right and so it sort of moves like what
you just described the versioning
problem
is propagated all through your
applications yep whereas I think with a
document passing it's more like you know
the versioning is in the document it's
still hard but at least you've kind of
gotten it out of your application right
and you don't have to recompile stuff
right I mean I've I've worked for
customer where it took a week to change
you know to add an attribute or data
structure because they had to rebuild it
if the rebuild redeploy retest you know
and the operators system guys have
actually run in production don't want to
take a new version unless they
absolutely have to so what do you think
about all those WS whatever standards
are they going to be as to put it
cynical as pervasive as all those core
bar things where only act like ten
percent of the facilities and services
have actually been implemented or twenty
percent so is this going to change now
or same thing I think it's gonna be the
same I think there's well I'm not a big
I'm a big fan of standards in the sense
that we need standards they're important
to the industry what I'm not a big fan
of is me personally working on them when
everybody said you know these oMG
meetings it's so awful to go so I've
been in oMG I've been in w3c you know I
don't think it's so much the
organization as it is just that the
process is political and social by
nature if you do get most people are
there to try to do reasonable work but
you do get people that are there
seemingly to make other people's lives
difficult I don't know and so you wind
up with kind of two issues one specs are
just hard to work on to begin with but I
think you also have people that are sort
of like professional standards people
and that's their entire job is making
standards so for them to start up a new
spec and say hey we need a standard in
this space it doesn't really you know
seem to affect them in the in the sense
like do we really need this are you
really thinking this through in the
webservice of space there
is still no architecture right there was
a WS architecture group that I was on in
the w3c years ago that really never
produced anything and without something
like that to kind of guide a coherent
picture right like where do you put the
specs how do they fit together and
things like that so I think there are a
lot of specs that are either going to be
very you know in very small niches or
just won't be used at all generally I
think you know the way the WS stuff has
been put together is kind of like you
get big companies that write the spec to
begin with and then bring it to a
standards body and you know I'd rather
it's better than the design by committee
you know starting from scratch and yeah
comitia but at the same time it's sort
of like you're kind of forced to start
with their assumptions and their designs
and so it has a good good and bad side
to it one comment I heard yesterday and
that was that and oMG standard is a
political document masking as a software
specification I like that it's very good
don't tell Richard so Lee that though
he's much larger than I am so how
important do you think our middleware
standards and tools today obviously you
need them at runtime to to ensure
quality of service but if you you know
adopt like a model driven approach like
the stuff doc Smith is talking about you
know you could argue that it doesn't
really matter what specific middleware
you're using from an API programmers
point of view because you have all those
abstractions and then you have a
generator that generates you know
whatever WSDL and then you have the web
service or it generates IDL
so any opinion there well I'm not a big
fan of the modeling stuff because it
just seems like it's been going on and
on for years and I don't know that
they're making really good progress I
know they're making some so Doug may be
unhappy with me for saying that but
but I think there is something and it
sort of goes back to what we did with
Arctic's you know the whole kind of
there's multiple middleware systems and
they need to be joined together and you
know systems like Arctic's can do that
yeah but I think the standards are still
very important because you get this
fragmentation in the enterprise due to
mergers and acquisitions they have to
you know different organizations with
their own purchasing decisions and then
you reorg and find you know this
organization bought all mq series or
something and this one's all korva now
they have to interoperate and how does
that work so I think especially in the
messaging side of things
there hasn't been any protocol standards
at all right so if you buy you know MQ
from one person and MQ from another or
JMS from anybody you're getting a
different protocol every time so you
know that's another thing that I'm
working on now is the advanced Message
Queuing protocol which was put together
by the financial community primarily
JPMorgan Chase & Company and that's on
its on its track or on the road I
suppose to be a standard no there's no
standards body associated with it yet if
there's an AMQP working group which has
got a number of companies involved
different from say JMS so what's the
differences it's actually at marketing
on the wire protocol for messaging okay
so anybody implementing a mq should
interoperate with anybody else and
biopore message passing - exactly yep or
for RPC right for messaging so there's a
cupid project in the Apache Incubator
open source project that implements a MQ
there's also some commercial products
from I know of one from I Maddox and so
there are implementations of these and
it's interesting because the standards
you know have been so important in the
sort of RPC
style of aware many years and now
messaging is finally getting standard so
I think it's going to have a very large
effect on the messaging area
the fact not only do you have a standard
but now you have this open source system
that's you know it's already there you
can go to Cupid at a incubator dot
Apache org look for the cupid project
SVN checkout and you actually have a
working broker at a written in Java
another one in C++ and clients in those
languages and in Ruby and Python so so
so this brings us to the question what
you're working focuses today it so I
think it says this this aim queue thing
well if I were if my manager were here
I'd say I'm a hundred percent on a MQ
cuz that's what he tells me every day in
reality I have always have a variety of
projects running yeah but most of my
time is on a MQ I have a I suppose it's
like a hobby but this dynamic language
stuff that I've been working on for
quite a while I just think they're
languages like Ruby and Python are just
very expressive you can say so much in
in so few lines of code so I've been
working like I did a JavaScript
server-side implementation for Celtics
and Celtics fire so you can write your
server implementation in JavaScript or
in Y for X which is a xml handling
language based over the top of
JavaScript and then I was working on
some Ruby clients for Arctic's and the
expressiveness is amazing like you doing
four or five lines of Ruby what 70 or 80
lines of C++ can do it so that's kind of
another project and then I always have
my columns to write and you know yeah
well I've been writing
it's called toward integration been
writing that for it'll be five years I
think in January and it's interesting
because it's like when Doug Schmidt and
I had a column for many years it was all
about korva yeah this columns a little
more general so it's about integration
it'll where I can cover a variety of
things so that's that you know comes up
every couple months I have to write one
of those
I used to do a lot more traveling and
speaking at conferences but been trying
to tone that down a bit
yeah Yahoo this year is the only one at
the joke on friends and it's really one
of the better conferences my favorite
yeah yeah what many people were cited I
would agree right yeah so before we wrap
this up let's let's maybe miss it so a
little bit so what's the role of so are
you see in the enterprise and and how I
mean you know there was this panel on
what's left to say on so I and and I got
the impression there is not very much to
say about so because it's kind of you
know components done right or whatever
so any take on that well I think so is
very important first of all but it's not
as hyped I'd say as some people would
like to make it you know it's it really
comes down to fairly fundamental I say
software engineering principles
componentization modularity loose
coupling you know nice cohesive services
put together and join together abscess
painting so I think you know the the
panel obviously I was on the panel
because the track I spoke in yeah but I
think the panel what was interesting to
me about both the track and the panel is
that we have a really good understanding
of the technology and the technical
hurdles to getting a Sowa in place we
don't have a real good understanding of
as the non-technical side you know
there's which would be well some of the
issues around you know which group in
the enterprise builds the services is
there group that gets paid to build
services for other groups does every
group build their own services what if
those groups have to interoperate some
point in the future data structures do
you have one sort of enterprise wide
agreement on what a customer profile
looks like versus every group having
their own
you can even get into issues like
certain managers may want control over
certain things that they are resisting
so uh because it sort of removes some of
their control or takes away part of
their empire things like that you might
have CEOs or c-level executives that
don't quite understand how SOIC an
affect their business yeah actually
could go both ways you could have people
have sort of never heard of it and
therefore don't even want to think about
it yeah or you might have the c-level
person who kind of hears about it and
says we have to do this and you know you
guys make it happen without any guidance
and without you know addressing these
non-technical issues in the organization
so is interesting in that track with it
I think all the speakers touched on that
and that's very important the whole
governance side of so aware you have
repositories that kind of here's your
services here's the policies for using
them and it's all tied into that so it's
interesting because many people talk
about SEO
SOAs being the alignment of business and
IT in his business driven stuff and I
never could relate to that very much
because I mean in antithetic it doesn't
say it doesn't say service or a business
it says social architecture architecture
but the organizational issues you
touched upon they're different from the
business issues and I think there are
certainly challenges yeah there I think
SOA is ultimately directed at making
business value you know so isn't that
true for any IT and right and SOA is one
way to do it and the fact that
architecture is in the name is probably
wrong maybe I think when I was at Joe
two years ago I gave a talk where I said
that SOA stands for service-oriented
architecture but that's actually not
what it is and I had a list of 12 things
that SOA isn't you know that was one of
them and I think that's some of the
backlash that SOA gets is it's somewhat
miss named you know it's really more
around identifying the services in your
business that are common across business
processes that can be reused across
processes and shared among groups and
it's really an ultimately and
tea cost saver right if you do it right
if you do it right yeah okay so anything
else you want to say one of us know
about your passion Natha well I
mentioned the dynamic language thing
that's that's really sort of big in my
mind I just think there's so much to it
and it may be you know an overreaction
from having years of C++ and Java and I
just that's that's all everyday but I
think that's an area I'm gonna be
working a lot more on going forward so
we're waiting for a car bomb mapping for
Ruby well there already is one for
Python okay okay thank you very much for
being on the show and thank you have a
good time staying with Ruby Thanks
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
Software Engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details